hi there I said in the last video that I
wants to talk a little bit about some of
the opportunities that lockdown good
borders and I do want to do that but in
thinking about that a whole bunch of
other stuff has come up and so there's
going to be more videos in this one I
want to sort of create what I believe to
be the context for the conversation
about the opportunities in lockdown and
by that I mean that there seems to be a
very widely held
miss apprehension in my opinion that in
a few weeks or a couple of months or
whatever everything is going to go back
to normal and this makes me very sad for
two reasons number one as I said in the
last video I think this is a glorious
opportunity to really take stock take a
step back and re-evaluate some of the
ways in which we do things but also I
think that this reliance on everything
is gonna go back to normal is rooted in
you know fear of the unknown and the
comfort of familiarity and I get it you
know we all we all have that it's
entirely understandable but I do think
it's profoundly misguided and so I'd
like to use this video just to spend a
few minutes not very long giving a
little glimpse into some of the
uncertainty and complexity that
surrounds all of this and it's my
contention that this is basically what
chaos looks like right that there are so
many possibilities that could emerge
from this right that is impossible to
predict with any certainty how this is
going to play out and I think that
anyone who is espousing opinions about
you know how things are going to look in
three months six months a year's time is
essentially talking out of their ass
they're just guessing right so yeah like
I said I want to spend a few minutes
just just just highlighting some of the
difficulty and uncertainty around all of
this so the virus itself first of all
[Music]
cars are starting to flatten out now
right and so governments they're going
to be tempted to start relaxing the
lockdowns in order to get the economy
going right and so how is that going to
play out
it's the lockdowns are relaxed is that
going to mean a resurgence in cases or
will testing be ramped up to the point
where you know quarantines can be
targeted and things can start you know
people can start going back to work and
so on don't know yet when people have
had the disease and recovered from it
what are the long-term consequences to
their health is there damage to the
respiratory system to their immune
system for example we don't know yet
when people have had it and recovered
from it are they immune to the disease
in perpetuity are they somewhat immune
to the disease so they don't get
symptoms but they can still be carriers
again all of this is unknown will a
vaccine be developed probably at some
point how long is it going to take don't
know how effective is it going to be
don't know for how long is it going to
be effective in any given individual
don't know how widely available is it
going to be how quickly can it be rolled
out globally don't know what will the
distribution of the vaccine be will it
be available first in rich countries and
in poor countries what does that mean
for travel what does that mean for the
transportation of goods don't know
whichever nation develops the vaccine
first how altruistic are they going to
be with that information or are they
going to seek to profit from it
politically financially whatever you
know imagine for example that an Iranian
laboratory comes up with a vaccine first
right are they going to be nice to the
Americans for example who have never
really been very nice to them right are
they going to just let them have it
freely or are they going to use that to
hold over them I mean this is you know
these kinds of these these kinds of
situations are going to emerge from this
chaos and depending on which direction
is taken that's gonna you join me a
profound change it could either be the
beginning of real collaboration and
cooperation and forgiveness of past sins
and all of that kind of thing or it can
be a pathway to war right it is very
very very different outcome so that's
kind of the point I want to make
there are all sorts of other unknowns
with the economy for example right all
of these people who are not getting paid
all of these businesses who are not
being receiving any food not been
receiving any revenue governments
response is broadly so far - this have
been don't worry about it you don't have
to pay your bills now you can sort it
out later but you still have to sort it
out later right these things are being
deferred not canceled there's no
moratorium there's no Jubilee and so
yeah that is going to lead to a whole
bunch of people not having jobs and you
have to claim right if you don't if
you've lost your job you have to claim
for whatever benefits in your country
who's processing all of these claims you
know the number of claims has gone up
three four five fold ten fold in some
places whose processing all these claims
are some of the staff are coming down
with the virus and everyone's being
isolated who knows these people are even
deemed essential personnel I don't know
so there's it's impossible to believe in
my opinion that things are gonna go back
to normal it is far far far more likely
that things are gonna change
dramatically now I don't know how
they're gonna change but I do think
they're gonna change and so this is kind
of the context that I was trying to put
the oppertunity idea into right when
your time is no longer being directed
entirely from the outside world if only
for a while what are you gonna do with
it when you don't have your job when you
don't have your routine you don't have
the daily trappings of your life who are
you in the absence of that what what is
actually important to you what do you
wish to hold primary in going forward in
these times of chaos these are the kinds
of questions that one can be asking
oneself during these kinds of times so
yeah I mean either I see there's two
basic choices that face people at the
moment right you've got a lot of time in
your hands a lot of thoughts swirling
around through your head normally you
don't have to listen to all that stuff
right is he busy doing other things but
yeah there's two responses here right
one is like I said stick your head in
the sand and just go all-in on the fact
that is all can go back to normal and
it's all going to be okay again and
maybe maybe who knows it's possible
that's exactly how it's going to
god I can think of nothing more
depressing than in three months we're
all back to arguing about brexit
but anyway yeah that's a possibility the
alternative is to in Joseph Campbell
language heed the call for action and
embark on a journey that will not only
you know prepare you for an uncertain
future but also enrich your life deepen
your relationships
expand your capacity all of this kind of
thing so you know seeing it as an
opportunity to embark on adventure
rather than hunkering down and being
fearful seems to me to be a better
response just one final thought the
notion I laid out earlier on about you
at the lab in Iran and the two
directions that we could take there I
mean that idea runs right down to the
level of you know am I gonna let my
neighbor have a roll or two of my toilet
paper or am I gonna board all of my 36
rolls or whatever to myself and so I
think it's really important to remember
that at some point the virus is gonna be
behind us right it's gonna be a thing of
the past but the decisions that we make
in the face of it could potentially stay
with us for a very very very long time
and so the less those decisions can be
rooted in fear of the unknown and a
desperate desire to get back to the
familiar and the more they can be
grounded in a spirit of adventure a
willingness to embrace the unknown and
to try new things and the more likely we
are to make good decisions in the long
run so yeah that's really all I have to
say for this one more coming like I said
but for now thank you very much daddy
for watching and see you soon